<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
      xmlns:webfeeds="http://webfeeds.org/rss/1.0">

 <title>Jeroen Mols</title>
 <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/"/>
 <icon>http://jeroenmols.com/img/profile.jpg</icon>
 <subtitle>Blog of Jeroen Mols focussed on Android development, open source and technology.</subtitle>
 <updated>2016-07-21T16:54:02+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://jeroenmols.com/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Jeroen Mols</name>
 </author>

 <webfeeds:cover image="http://jeroenmols.com/img/profile.jpg" />
 <webfeeds:icon>http://jeroenmols.com/img/profile.jpg</webfeeds:icon>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Turn Android into an awesome GPS</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/07/21/cyclinggps/"/>
   <updated>2016-07-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/07/21/cyclinggps</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/cyclinggps/cyclinggps.png" alt="Turn Android into an awesome GPS">
     
     <p>Cycling is all about exploring: visiting new places and making existing routes more fun with better streets. So there must be an app that allows to plan your route and start cycling right? Think again... there is currently no solution that offers turn by turn navigation for cyclists.</p>

<p>As I had an old Android device laying around, I decided to repurpose that and convert it into a GPS that:</p>

<ul>
<li>tracks my activity</li>
<li>imports gpx tracks created on my computer</li>
<li>offers turn by turn navigation (screen + voice)</li>
</ul>

<p>This blogpost will detail how I use <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=net.osmand">OsmAnd</a> and <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.ttxapps.dropsync">Dropsync</a> to create new tracks with minimal effort. Further I&#39;ll also describe the gear I use in order to make this work.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/07/21/cyclinggps/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Testing made sweet with a Mockito</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/24/droidcondetalk/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/24/droidcondetalk</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/droidconde16talk/droidcondetalk.png" alt="Testing made sweet with a Mockito">
     
     <p>At Droidcon Berlin 2016 I had a great time talking about testing using the <a href="http://mockito.org/">Mockito</a> framework. While the talk wasn&#39;t recorded unfortunately, the great folks at <a href="https://voicerepublic.com/series/droidcon-berlin-2016">Voice Republic</a> recorded an audio version which you can listen to as a podcast or together with the slides.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/24/droidcondetalk/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Droidcon Berlin recap</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/18/droidconde/"/>
   <updated>2016-06-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/18/droidconde</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/droidconde16/droidconde.png" alt="Droidcon Berlin recap">
     
     <p>Having founded the entire Droidcon franchise in 2009, Droidcon Berlin is a magical conference to be at. Not only do they have an awesome lineup of speakers (including yours truly). But they also organize great after hour events. Further they&#39;re the first conference ever where I didn&#39;t have any Wi-Fi issues (looking at you #io16).</p>

<p>As there were four different tracks, it was obviously not possible to attend every session. But I did notice some general themes and would like to share my personal highlights with you.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/06/18/droidconde/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Efficiently reducing your method count</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/05/06/methodcount/"/>
   <updated>2016-05-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/05/06/methodcount</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/methodcount/methodcount.png" alt="Efficiently reducing your method count">
     
     <p>As green field projects are a rare breed, chances are that you&#39;ve inherited a legacy code base. If you&#39;re as lucky as me, that code base has over 65k methods causing the build times to be boringly slow.</p>

<p>Today I would like to show how you can visualize your current method count and understand what libraries are eating up the largest part of that. Next it&#39;s time to reduce said method count and remove that nasty multidex solution once and for all.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/05/06/methodcount/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Droidcon Italy recap</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/04/08/droidconit/"/>
   <updated>2016-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/04/08/droidconit</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/droidconit16/droidconit.png" alt="Droidcon Italy recap">
     
     <p>A conference about our favorite Green little robots? In sunny Italy? With great food and a party? Yeah, I can image how you must feel in case you missed it... I on the other hand was fortunate enough to attend and speak at this awesome conference.</p>

<p>With over 770 attendees and four different tracks, it was obviously not possible to attend every session. But I did notice some general themes and would like to share my personal highlights with you.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/04/08/droidconit/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A successful XML naming convention</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/03/07/resourcenaming/"/>
   <updated>2016-03-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/03/07/resourcenaming</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/resourcenaming/resourcenaming.png" alt="A successful XML naming convention">
     
     <p>Do you remember the last time you had to dig into <code>strings.xml</code> to find the right String to use? Or that you manually had to go over all drawables to find the one you needed?</p>

<p>Whenever we start a new project, we take a lot of care in setting up our architecture, CI, build flavors,... But do you also have a strategy to name your resources?</p>

<p>You should! Because the lack of XML namespaces, makes managing Android resources tedious. And causes things to grow out of control easily, especially in large projects.</p>

<p>So let&#39;s introduce a simple scheme that will solve your pains.</p>

<ul>
<li>easy lookup of any resource (autocomplete)</li>
<li>logical, predictable names</li>
<li>clean ordering of resources</li>
<li>strongly typed resources</li>
</ul>

<p>This blogpost will explain the mechanism, its advantages, limitations and provide an easy to use cheat sheet.</p>




     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/03/07/resourcenaming/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Git as a secure private Maven repository</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/02/05/wagongit/"/>
   <updated>2016-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/02/05/wagongit</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/wagongit/wagongit.png" alt="Git as a secure private Maven repository">
     
     <p>As my previous blogposts already covered how to set up a private Maven repository, you might wonder &quot;Why again a Maven blogpost?&quot;. Well that&#39;s a fair question and the answer is twofold:</p>

<ol>
<li>Backup mechanism, to ensure you never ever loose releases.</li>
<li>Remote access outside of your local network (intranet).</li>
</ol>

<p>And Git implicitly solves both! :)</p>

<p>I&#39;ll demonstrate how to configure Bitbucket as a free private remote Maven repository and automate everything in one simple Gradle script.</p>


     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/02/05/wagongit/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Year in review 2015</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/01/29/yearinreview/"/>
   <updated>2016-01-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/01/29/yearinreview</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/yearinreview15/yearinreview15.png" alt="Year in review 2015">
     
     <p>Finally found the time to write my <code>year in review</code>. #insomnia</p>

<p>2015 was a huge year for me! I even dare to say the biggest one of my life so far as I became a father of a lovely daughter Lene. Its really hard to over state how big of an impact that has on your life and how fantastic it is to see your own baby grow (and recognize parts of yourself in her). This obviously also explains my late <code>year in review</code> post. #perfectexcuse</p>

<p>On a technical level I also fared well and I&#39;m very happy with what I&#39;ve been able to accomplish:</p>

<ul>
<li>Created an library with &gt;500 stars on  <a href="https://github.com/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera">Github</a></li>
<li>Started my own blog and <a href="http://jeroenmols.com">website</a></li>
<li>Featured blogpost in <a href="http://androidweekly.net/issues/issue-165">Android Weekly</a></li>
<li>Spoke at my first conference <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jeroenmols/distributing-to-a-public-or-private-maven-repository">Droidcon Paris</a></li>
<li>Actively started using <a href="https://twitter.com/molsjeroen">twitter</a> and gained &gt;100 followers</li>
<li>Gained &gt;1000 reputation on <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/users/2771851/jmols">stackoverflow</a></li>
<li>Landed a new job at Philips Hue</li>
<li>Learned Xamarin and built a cross platform app</li>
<li>Wrote the worlds latest <code>year in review</code> post</li>
</ul>

<p>Next year will be more challenging as my daughter has become a lot more effective at grabbing my attention than my laptop. However I want to increase my efforts contributing back to the community by speaking at more conferences and writing more blogposts. Finally I also want to visit Google IO, which is about time I got there, don&#39;t you agree? ;)</p>

<p>As always you can reach me <a href="https://twitter.com/molsjeroen">@molsjeroen</a> on twitter, or leave a comment below!</p>

     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2016/01/29/yearinreview/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Level up GitHub builds with CI and code coverage</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/11/13/traviscoveralls/"/>
   <updated>2015-11-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/11/13/traviscoveralls</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/traviscoveralls/traviscoveralls.png" alt="Level up GitHub builds with CI and code coverage">
     
     <p>Wouldn&#39;t you love to have your open source projects built automatically by a continuous integration server? And to have a detailed code coverage report for all your unit tests? Even when someone generated a pull request? And how about having cool badges to show off all of this?</p>

<p><center><a href="https://travis-ci.org/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera"><img src="https://travis-ci.org/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera.svg?branch=master" alt="Build Status"></a> <a href="https://coveralls.io/github/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera?branch=master"><img src="https://coveralls.io/repos/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera/badge.svg?branch=master&amp;service=github" alt="Coverage Status"></a></center></p>

<p>Actually, all of this a breeze to set up, once you understand what works and what doesn&#39;t. It is even completely free for open source projects!</p>

<p>In less than half an hour, this blogpost will add CI and code coverage to your projects, just like I did for my own library <a href="https://github.com/JeroenMols/LandscapeVideoCamera">LandscapeVideoCamera</a>. While this article focusses on Android, the material presented here can quite easily be extended to a broader scope.</p>


     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/11/13/traviscoveralls/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Getting the most out of Artifactory</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/13/artifactory2/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/13/artifactory2</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/artifactory2/artifactory2.png" alt="Getting the most out of Artifactory">
     
     <p>My previous <a href="/blog/2015/08/06/artifactory/">blog post</a> described how to set up your own private Maven repository with Artifactory in 30 minutes. This second and final part will make things more interesting and take your setup to the next level.</p>

<p>You will learn how to:</p>

<ul>
<li>handle library projects with dependencies</li>
<li>securely provide username and password</li>
<li>work with snapshot and release builds</li>
<li>configure custom repositories</li>
<li>manage user access</li>
</ul>

<p>All source code is <a href="https://github.com/JeroenMols/ArtifactoryExample">available on Github</a> as usual.</p>

<p>Note that the material presented here can quite easily be extended to be applicable beyond Android.</p>


     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/13/artifactory2/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>A private Maven repository for Android in 30 min</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/06/artifactory/"/>
   <updated>2015-08-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/06/artifactory</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/artifactory/artifactory.png" alt="A private Maven repository for Android in 30 min">
     
     <p>Setting up your own Maven repository and uploading artifacts to it is quite a daunting task. As I went through this experience myself recently, I want to help others in setting up their own Maven repository via <a href="http://www.jfrog.com/open-source/">Artifactory</a> and automate uploading artifacts using Gradle.</p>

<p>In less than 30 minutes you will have a fully operational private Maven repository and have configured your Gradle buildscripts to upload your Android library artifacts.</p>

<p>Note that the material presented here can quite easily be extended to be applicable in a broader scope beyond Android.</p>


     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/08/06/artifactory/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How I created my blog</title>
   <link href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/04/25/blog-creation/"/>
   <updated>2015-04-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/04/25/blog-creation</id>
   <content type="html"><![CDATA[
     
        <img src="http://jeroenmols.com/img/blog/jekyll.png" alt="How I created my blog">
     
     <p>For quite some months, I&#39;ve been planning to create a website and start blogging about the things I&#39;m passionate about. Last week, I finally decided to setup a <a href="http://jeroenmols.github.io">portfolio</a> and <a href="http://jeroen.mols.github.io/blog">blog</a> using GitHub pages and Jekyll.</p>

<p>Since I&#39;m an Android and not a web developer, the first blogging subject wasn&#39;t hard to find: challenges I came across in setting up this website and blog.</p>

<blockquote>
<p><strong>Disclaimer:</strong> Eventually I had to use a workaround - that&#39;s why I don&#39;t build websites professionally - but I strongly believe in a <em>Just do It</em> mentality and then learn/improve as you go.</p>
</blockquote>


     <a href="http://jeroenmols.com/blog/2015/04/25/blog-creation/">Continue reading</p>]]>
   </content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
